<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-13T08:14:07+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rehmat Singh Chawla</title><subtitle>Welcome to my website! I study Physics, make coffee, write poetry and generally vibe. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Rap and Poetry</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Rap-and-Poetry/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rap and Poetry"/><published>2024-01-17T08:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-17T08:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Rap%20and%20Poetry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Rap-and-Poetry/"><![CDATA[<p>I’d been writing the occasional poem for a long time when I discovered rap music, and at first I did not draw a connection between the two. But less than an year later, when I penned my first rap (for a Chemistry assignment, no less), I realised how similar it was to when I used to write poetry. This motivated me to pick up the pen again - more seriously this time - and led to the most bountiful era my poetry has seen.<br/> I’ve realised that my works often have dual qualities allowing for rap-like readings as well as poetic performances, and I want to explore this further. In response to the occasional dissenting opinions, I composed the following piece - and well, I’ll let it speak for itself.</p> <div class="poem"> <b>Rap and Poetry</b><br/><br/>Some would like to draw a line between rap and poetry<br/>I would like to live where they would dig the pit<br/>I’ll straddle the line with devices and disses<br/>Hop over it and back like I’m skipping to a beat.<br/>My power lies in my pen, and it can’t be taken from me<br/>I’ll write lyrical epics and literary rhapsodies,<br/>Something which could be sung to a crowd with a beat, or appreciated as an artistic symphony.<br/>As interdisciplinary as can be<br/>That’s the only way I can ink me.</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The two rhythmic genres are considered disjoint by many, but I want to explore their intersection.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prisoner of my mind</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Prisoner-of-my-mind/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prisoner of my mind"/><published>2024-01-16T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-16T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Prisoner%20of%20my%20mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Prisoner-of-my-mind/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>Prisoner of my mind</b><br/><br/>O prisoner of my mind, what raven-song you sing?<br/>A mockery, a tragedy, of quests to find my wings<br/>You’d have me play the clipper, my company the cage<br/>And not satisfy till you have me drowned, in sorrow or in rage<br/><br/>Imprisoner of my mind, what command you to-day?<br/>That I should lash unjustly, or whelm and lifeless stay?<br/>That I should starve, insomniate, or sloth my while away?<br/>Do what you will, but do to me, drive not my friends astray<br/><br/>Master of my mind, what lessons do you bring?<br/>Tell tales of my fallacies, so hate may seep in<br/>I’ll stab me till I’m mastered, so hand me, if not blade,<br/>Shards from the mirrors I would shatter to be great</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Would life not be a cakewalk if I could listen to myself?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bad With Words</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Bad-With-Words/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bad With Words"/><published>2023-08-23T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-23T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Bad%20With%20Words</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Bad-With-Words/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>Bad With Words</b><br/><br/>Bad with words<br/><br/>I’m bad with words<br/>You may be surprised,<br/>A poet claiming he doesn’t know how to write?<br/>It’s not so much my vocab, or the grammar being right,<br/>But making my words mean what I want them to mean<br/>My light-absorbing orbs stare down the blinking line, black on white<br/>I can’t tell if I should delete to the left or write to the right<br/>Emails not worth minutes have taken me nights<br/><br/>Emails, yes, that’s where people say they don’t know what to say,<br/>But say, you want C to do B by time A,<br/>Then so you say, make it a little polite, send and be on your way<br/><br/>That’s not the hard part, but oh, if I start to say what’s hard I’ll never get anywhere<br/>Mostly because I’d stick a TWSS into any conversation I’m near<br/>(TWTS?)<br/>But also because I’m bad at saying things so that you hear what I want you to hear<br/><br/>Let me break it down, I suck at conversations, I think too slow and miss my chances,<br/>Laugh too much, and when I do empathise I seem unresponsive<br/>Unresponsive when asked for opinion or advice,<br/>And when I respond I doubt every word I say<br/>(Though that’s a story for another day)<br/><br/>I’ve never added value to conversations, lest I can twist them to myself<br/>I talk too much about myself, well<br/>It is the only subject I know kinda well<br/>But then it comes back to the well of all the ways I’m bad with words<br/>To beg for a job you gotta overwhelm and convince them of your worth<br/>And I lack the words to make me worth a dwell - or maybe just lack faith in my worth?<br/><br/>Well, this has been far too many words without much worth<br/>You’re welcome to leave now, apologies for keeping you long<br/>TWSS<br/>Sorry, couldn’t resist<br/>Maybe I could have if I had something more worthwhile to say<br/>But I’m just that bad with words.<br/></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm supposed to be good with language, as a poet and avid reader. But I don't always feel that way.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nuts about you</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Nuts-about-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nuts about you"/><published>2023-05-14T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-14T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Nuts%20about%20you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Nuts-about-you/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>Nuts about you</b><br/><br/>Nuts about you<br/><br/>You took my breath away<br/>And left me wanting more<br/><br/>I'd known nothing like it,<br/>This feeling that now enveloped me<br/>Overwhelming, it mingled emotions in ways I'd never conceived<br/>Ecstasy in what had been, longing for what more could be<br/>Passion, nay, an urge to make reality what now flooded my dreams<br/><br/>You're to thank, and to blame<br/>There were days you drove me insane<br/>I had you, but it was never enough<br/>I always wanted just another taste, I wanted too much<br/>Is containing love a fool's game?<br/>Or was I the fool who refused to play?<br/><br/>You were the salsa to my nachos, you made me make sense<br/>I could go on with the food metaphors but none compared to you<br/>They still don't<br/>You seem timeless<br/>Maybe that was the problem.<br/>You were timeless, and I aged<br/>Maybe I just don't keep well<br/>Moldy, you called me<br/><br/>I won't point fingers<br/>Hurt went both ways<br/>But it's behind us now<br/>And we've found our place<br/>Amid knives and flames<br/>Hand-in-hand we'll tread<br/>And you'll still take my breath away<br/>Nutella, you glorious hazlenut-cocoa spread<br/><br/>- Bread<br/></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Romance is a frequent theme in poetry, and I felt it was high time I gave it a go with my own flair.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Once more, rise</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Once-more-rise/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Once more, rise"/><published>2023-04-18T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Once%20more-rise</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Once-more-rise/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>Once more, rise</b><br/><br/>Broken and jaded and humiliated,<br/>I stand at sundown, head bent, with my spark faded,<br/>Body heavy as if my failures I carry,<br/>“To stand is useless,” I deem, and fall.<br/>Down I come, hopes and all.<br/>Among worms I sprawl,<br/>The air turned rock, not a gust to ruffle, what peace, I made the right call.<br/><br/>Yet someone wished for a squall.<br/>Someone called my blanket a wall,<br/>Wished to stand up tall, loudly call, every challenger brawl!<br/>What foolishness, I rebuke inwards, to dream so big when I am, so small,<br/>Failure that I am, after all.<br/><br/>Resolute, I looked up, to show myself an unforgiving sky<br/>But instead I saw stars, eyes looking into my eyes,<br/>Fly!<br/>I heard, soar, in joy cry!<br/>But I can’t, claim I, and I reply,<br/>Prove it. I laugh.<br/>How sly.<br/><br/>So I raise myself<br/>And I stand up straight<br/>And straight at the moon I stare,<br/>Witness, Diana!<br/>My oath to make heavy,<br/>The empty scabbard I wear.<br/><br/>With heavy arms, though getting lighter, <br/>Grab the rusted blade tossed aside<br/>It’s heavy, I can’t, it’s too much for me,<br/>Are just thoughts, they shall be like tides.<br/>What a bore it would be to lie down again,<br/>So I swing to the ground and the skies<br/>And I’ll swing till I soar, come blaze or downpour,<br/>Sweat drenched, I swing till sunrise.<br/>Once more, I rise.</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the days when your failures feel overwhelming.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Metered Metric Space</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/metered-metric-space/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Metered Metric Space"/><published>2023-02-22T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-22T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/metered-metric-space</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/metered-metric-space/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>The Metered Metric Space</b><br/><br/> Might be rare to write a poem merely to prove a point,<br/> But I’m here to prove a theorem, maths and words are not disjoint.<br/> Manifolds and metaphors, they seem mistakes to mix?<br/> My my, you’re clearly new to meters and metrics, kiddo!<br/><br/> My rhythm is so radical with heptameter lines,<br/> Not even the Lagrangian could minimise my rhymes!<br/> I'll integrate so many terms into lines two to the fourth,<br/> Best hold on to your integers and prepare to be floored!<br/><br/> I'll alliterate algebra, turn your products into powers,<br/> Dual-wield bra ket vector spaces and personified flowers.<br/> When I call mugs donuts it's metaphor and topology,<br/> My Haikus so symmetric you'd think it's group theory.<br/><br/> Call me Euclid, how I'll be redefining the genre's meta,<br/> Limitless in trying to be the best, so call me an epsilon-delta.<br/> My words strike like functions spike, yup that's a simile,<br/> I differentiate to the dirac, that’s why they call me Green.<br/> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><category term="math"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A friend once challenged me saying that I couldn't mix poetry and math. I proved him wrong.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Polyglottic Poetry</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/sting-poem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polyglottic Poetry"/><published>2023-02-06T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-06T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/sting-poem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/sting-poem/"><![CDATA[<p>One thing I love is using multiple languages in a single poem. While I’m yet limited by my lack of polyglottism (I’m certain that’s not really a word, but then it should be), I do have one attempt at such a poem that’s dear to my heart, it was the poem with which I realised I could write meaningful, interesting poems and that I enjoyed it a lot. Presenting,</p> <div class="poem"> <b>Sometimes you just like the sting</b><br/><br/> Hear me out, I'm not a masochist,<br/> I'm not out here advertising eating fists,<br/> Nor hurting yourself for the fun of it,<br/> But the sting, it reminds you you exist.<br/><br/> Doesn't it?<br/> Hasn't it,<br/> Ever woken your head and senses?<br/> Snapped, right cracked, stupor you out of,<br/> Wind rushes past, ridding the pillow soft,<br/> Open wide eyes, disappear lies,<br/> like foggy skies with bright sunrise?<br/> Il a pour me, mon ami.<br/> Il a pour me, loving it, je suis.<br/><br/> Sometimes you just like the sting.<br/> Because this we know, you and I,<br/> Without the thorns, the petals die;<br/> Alchemy's fundamental law holds true,<br/> As you give to me, I must lose for you,<br/> So when it stings, I know for sure,<br/> That what I'm getting is true, and<br/> My bruises keep wanting more.<br/> So, mon ami, do you see?<br/> Pourquoi c'est comme ça avec me?<br/><br/> But before I go, I'll leave you with this,<br/> The sting may be nice, but not memory miss,<br/> A little bruise heals easy, not so the cracks and pains,<br/> Of bones, hearts broken - sometimes never heal again.<br/><br/> </div> <p>Translations:<br/> “il a pour me” = “it has for me”<br/> “mon ami” = “my friend”<br/> “je suis” = “I am”<br/> “pourquoi c’est comme ça avec me?” = “why it is like this with me?”<br/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><category term="french"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A (barely) bilingual poem, hopefully the first of many.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/introduction-poem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction"/><published>2023-02-06T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-06T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/introduction-poem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/introduction-poem/"><![CDATA[<p>Good evening, folks. Another post before I go for a much-needed nap. This is a little poem/rap I wrote to introduce myself in a WhatsApp group concerning the Literary Arts club at my college (Literati).</p> <div class="poem"> Heyo, folks of Literati, I’ve got words to say,<br/> Myself Rehmat Singh Chawla, though call me Bread you may,<br/> My branch, it would be EP, my home though, the bookshelf,<br/> Now allow me, words flowing free, to introduce myself!<br/><br/> Incoming!<br/> The volleyball-loving weeb,<br/> Not tricks, just words up his sleeve,<br/> Poetry, rap, stories, you name it, I’m up for it all!<br/> But keep your expectations low, I’m in the amateurs’ hall.<br/><br/> I’ve got no<br/> Favourite story, it’s been so long since I picked one up!<br/> Interesting history, might feel bland, plain milk in a cup!<br/> But words make me feel alive, I jive,<br/> This club’s where I’m gonna thrive!<br/><br/> There’s a bit more to me, I love sweet stuff, and coffee, well,<br/> It’s gotta be a little divine for a drink to shine, froth, and flavour so,<br/> They call it an addiction, I say it’s soothing my soul, or rather,<br/> Exciting, transforming, igniting my psyche of fighting,<br/> Makes me wanna pick up a pen, and start writing!<br/><br/> This is it for now, but it ain’t all, chief.<br/> Five paragraphs this time, next will be six.<br/> Did I seem too arrogant? Sorry, that’s just mischief,<br/> Now I’ve spent way too long on this, back to Physics.<br/> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Allow me to present a brief glimpse of myself.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About writing poems on spit</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2022/About-writing-poems-on-spit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About writing poems on spit"/><published>2022-09-18T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-18T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2022/About%20writing%20poems%20on%20spit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2022/About-writing-poems-on-spit/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>About writing poems on spit</b><br/><br/>Shall we write a poem together<br/>About spit, or something else?<br/>It would shake someone up<br/>Or make people laugh<br/><br/>It’s better than writing poetry which makes people sad<br/>And worried<br/>And they say, "Are you alright?"<br/>Poems are not written to seek or show reassurances<br/><br/>Why do you write poems?<br/>You say you don’t<br/>I find poetry<br/>In your steps, in your hair,<br/>In the flourish with which you end your signature when the bank won’t be scanning it<br/>In the contact names which are so telling, and telling when they are decidedly not<br/>You are poetry<br/>And I would like to read a part of you<br/><br/>It is sunset<br/>The clouds don’t let me know for sure<br/>My phone buzzes<br/>You have written down a part of you<br/>And despite what I preach<br/>I want to ask you<br/>Are you alright?<br/>And hear something more than the Yes I know will be a lie<br/><br/>Perhaps<br/>We should have written the poem on spit after all<br/></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[TBA]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Efficient</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2022/Efficient/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Efficient"/><published>2022-07-07T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-07T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2022/Efficient</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2022/Efficient/"><![CDATA[<p>I oft feel a pressure, arising from my own ambitions, to be more productive, more efficient. And so I push myself, sometimes in odd ways, sometimes too harshly. These efforts don’t always bear fruit, and this can be discouraging - I realised one day that I needed a paradigm shift in my path of self-improvement.</p> <div class="poem"> <b>Efficient</b><br/><br/><br/><br/>56 things on my to-do list<br/>I’ve got the drive, can do it all if I be quick,<br/>Might be sleep-deprived, just hold on till the caffeine hits<br/>24 are plenty, if I use them fit<br/>If I wisely split, if I schedule it,<br/>Lost 2 feeling lazy? I can make up for it,<br/>Lose nothing,<br/>Sacrifice nothing, it’s an art,<br/>To use every moment, strategically impart<br/>Every second on etching a mark with my metal<br/>Impress with intelligence, make up for defects<br/>For fissures and scratches that smother my prowess<br/>With which every task that I take I still decorate<br/><br/>And I still decorate every day with failures<br/>And I still end days in unchecked boxes and tears<br/>And every morning I race the clock, and race my fears<br/>And I push every second, but the list grows unsheared<br/><br/>Every step can be studying, every rest another page,<br/>Treat meals like side-quests, a conversation a cage.<br/>This is the right way, isn’t it?<br/>To make the most of the time that’s given,<br/>To strive to be more efficient?<br/>Maybe I could be the genius everyone says is wrong!<br/>Ah frick, that really is just arrogance.<br/><br/>An ego too eloquent<br/>A mind with no pessimist<br/>A focus misplaced,<br/>A hope too unmerited<br/>And time is yet limited<br/>So be slow and rigorous<br/>Fix what is broken<br/>And you’ll see efficient.<br/></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I like to push myself to be productive. Does it work?]]></summary></entry></feed>